[Music]
last month rebel wisdom put out a series
of films with the integral philosopher
Ken Wilber Jamie Wheel is recognized as
one of the world's leading experts on
peak performance and transformation as
the head of the flow Genome Project and
author of the Pulitzer prize-nominated
stealing fire he has a long history with
integral theory going back two decades
and worked for one of the only two
integral management consulting firms
attempting to bring the principles to
business leaders he reflects on the
legacy of integral it seems to be the
case as we move into these you know
nominally transpersonal communities is
that all of these thought leaders who
have been breaking trail right they've
but they brought they brought through
something profound something unique
something useful they bringing a tool to
our shared collective and by default and
or by design we're all wounded healers
we all need the thing that we've built
more than anybody else needs it and I
think that that same case is probably
true for Ken and rather than having the
people who have experienced and
benefited from integral theory then rise
up in some sort of unreconciled slay the
father angry child dynamic can there be
instead the sense of hey wow your life's
work has lit things up in me has helped
guide my path right has brought me to
places I never had imagined and perhaps
can we then turn around and give back
the wounded healer the realized gift
that they offered in the first place and
not needs to not no need to knock them
down off pedestals and no need to kind
of reclaim our gold and kind of Angry
and dysfunctional ways but to say thank
you so much and let us return the favor
let us return academic acknowledgement
let us return community let us rich
love appreciation affection and
challenge
let us show up as the humans you've been
writing about all along and let's help
you take that final step for yourself we
don't all need all of our teachers to be
Moses leading people to the promised
land and getting stuck on the edge we
can actually welcome the folks that help
guide us to that land - to the potty
itself
so Jamie great to speak to you again
from Texas shown we recently put out a
film with Ken Wilber looking at Jordan
Pederson and the intellectual dark web
and what I think is a really important
piece like I've been certainly very
influenced by integral and think that
the developmental framework has a lot to
add to this emergent conversation that
Jordan Pederson has helped to kind of
spark the intellectual dark where as
part of it and I'm I know that you've
got a background with the integral
community and you're also one of the
most inspiring thinkers that we've met
in the time that we've been doing this I
was really impressed with the pieces
that we put out with you I think you're
holding a really key piece so I want and
I I'm fascinated you have a history with
integral as well I wonder if you might
want to sort of go through that for us
sure I mean I think I was I was actually
teaching at a boarding school in
California right after grad school so I
was in my early 20s and the headmaster
gave me Ken's brief history of
everything and said you might want to
read this and I and I jumped into it and
found that his descriptions of upper
stages of development and in
particularly I think he talked about the
aftershocks of ego death experiences and
the little ghosts that come back
afterwards and I remember it was such a
lifesaver for me at the time and then
dived in that book and I think it was
probably the densest thing I'd ever read
for fun you know not actually assigned
and that really opened my open my eyes
and open my world to everything from a
validation of interior experiences to
the notion of adult development and
vertical development and the sort of
sense that we don't just stop at puberty
or stop you know in our 20s and and
found it immensely valuable as an
initial kind of orienting framework and
then even sort of virusscan on thinking
and making sense of things and then you
went a bit more deeply into it as well I
think we did we were you know educators
by you know I was sort of historian
anthropologist by academic training and
then was working deeply
in basically developmentally informed
education ranging from Montessori to
Knowles which is sort of like an
outward-bound
kind of version of you know how do you
take people into expeditionary
environments and and learn and train and
then play a role with the integral
education community standing that up
which was a kind of a subset or branch
of Ken's integral Institute in the kind
of early 2000s and then as a result of
that work was actually recruited by one
of only two sort of truly integral
management consulting firms and then
went into the corporate space along with
John Mackey who was the founder of Whole
Foods that started the conscious
capitalism movement and we worked within
the young presidents organization which
is a global organization of business
leaders that's very it's quite powerful
they control about nine trillion dollars
in global market cap and we conducted a
series of experiments over the better
part of a decade on how do you bring
integrally informed development
leadership organization and
communication into high-growth
businesses and help the capitalists
become a little more conscious so it's
been a wild ride and a fun experiment
yeah because I I guess the the
interesting thing about both Jordan
Peterson and the intellectual diet over
in this kind of networked conversation
is that it's it's kind of open to fit
it's in the new digital age so it's got
to be open to feedback it's got to be
open to evolution and that's I guess
what I'm really interested in in being
part of that cuz I think integral has a
really interesting and valuable point to
bring but there are also I'm sure
lessons that can be learned of integral
successes and integrals failures because
there was a huge high point of it
probably in the 90s and 2000's and the
question is whether it had the impact
that it that it should have had all
could have had and also what we can
learn from it if we're involved in some
of the same questions now and I I guess
you've you've had a lot of experience
right at the sharp end of that
conversation yeah absolutely
and and it does feel there's a couple of
things it feels like
the thought leaders today and whether
that's in the crypto space and thinking
about kind of decentralized
organizations or whether it's an
existential risk or even kind of in more
sophisticated versions of personal
development and leadership development I
have noticed that even without teasing
it out or calling it out it kind of
bubbles up in conversations that a
significant number of those folks took
on and can seriously considered integral
frameworks at some point earlier in
their life so I think that's just kind
of interesting to note equally
interesting to note no one is branding
their work their movement or ideas in
that way these days and so that's just
kind of a you know a curiosity but I
think also a four hat tip to the the
ongoing significance of that sort of
integral Institute diaspora you know I
think it was sort of a Schumpeter's
creative destruction writ large where an
awful lot of fascinating people were
drawn together around that movement when
it imploded exploded depending on your
point of view its scattered and
dispersed a lot of those people but the
relationships and the shared ideas have
persisted and borne a lot of fruit yeah
you said what I thought was a really
beautiful metaphor that a lot of people
breaking trail are running an integral
OS yeah and I think some of the simplest
thing is a the complexity of thinking in
those ways the valuing that there are
interior experiences that are as
important and map and track as exterior
experiences and that things that we
might talk about in the realms of policy
government business you know aka sort of
third-person structures are also
informed by and connected to culture and
interior psychology and just that
ability I mean fundamentally the four
quadrants of Ken's model there's insides
and outsides of singulars and plurals
that alone I think is game-changing and
then a few others if you know what Ken
calls the pre Tron's fallacy you'd like
don't confuse irrational things with
post rational things
and particularly you know the terrain
that we read about in a stealing fire
talking about the psychedelic
Renaissance the explosion and state
seeking and non-ordinary states like wim
HOF and breathing you name it really
this kind of immense hunger these days
for all things non ordinary is really
important to distinguish between what is
regressive and just going back to kind
of magical thinking and what is
progressive we're truly stepping into
some increasingly complex and helpful
new ways of looking at stuff and you
mentioned a few there but what do you
think of a are the really crucial pieces
that integral provides what are the what
are the most important parts of that
integral os I think I just named them
really I mean I think it's the idea of
interiors and exteriors and they're
they're equally important to be
considered that notion of the pre trans
fallacy don't confuse less sophisticated
things for more sophisticated things
simply because they're not standard
business as usual the notions of adult
development or vertical development were
both I think they were helpfully wrong
is the simplest way to say it and I was
actually just having a conversation with
Zack Stein who studied at Harvard did
his doctorate under Bob Keegan and some
of the other developmental theorists and
you know Ken's model which he then kind
of piggy back to spiral dynamics and
those kinds of things the idea that
there's such a thing as second-tier that
second tier is this momentous leap that
if you're even here this conference
we're reading this book aka one of us
you are parentheses at least cognitively
at second tier I think that created far
more problems than it's solved and it
basically was like crack for Asperger's
kids you know the idea of getting a
contact high from reading Ken's stuff
and getting to see yourself on a map and
position yourself up and away from no
matter what the disclaimers were and
there were plenty of disclaimers the
reality as that showed up in culture and
in practice resulted in a bunch of
dissociated eggheads masquerading as as
Jedi and thinking that they could solve
the world from the
of a whiteboard and that I think was you
know part of the cracks in the
foundation I guess I was relatively late
to to discovering Ken's work and I've
been very impressed with it but it but I
also get a sense like a lot of integral
forums or integral conversations just
tend to degenerate into I'm more
integral than you this sort of integral
one-up developmental one-upmanship
yeah and that was what was sort of
precious about it you know within the
integral kind of core community you know
Ken talking about things that were
awkward kosher you know on the one nine
totally get it a rigorous rigorous
methodology you want to make sure people
aren't cutting corners or sloppily
applying it but that rigidity then led
to effectively aqua Maoism where the
only things that got the stamp of
approval were some of the most
derivative unimaginative like let me
take the discipline or vertical I'm
apart of let me run it through the aqua
sausage grinder spit out all the you
know the expected truisms and critiques
and I've added nothing of substance to
my field but I've just complied with the
certification on the top and I think
there were only a handful of people that
I was aware of Sean Huggins was one Zach
Stein was another there were the number
of people who were actually creating
unique or interesting content within the
Aqua world outside of Kenan was very low
and I think part of that was the you
know this is pre blockchain plea pre
emphasis on D central is a decentralized
sense-making or collective intelligence
so it was very hierarchically throttled
and I think that choked a lot of the
potential messy but essential life
that's now happened since outside the
walls of that close could close
container and is that because eventually
many people kind of confuse the map for
the territory so you just end up loading
it you end up having to produce in a
certain language and a certain set of
dogmas that then crushes the life out of
the emergent phenomenon or what is it
well I think I think your description of
what happened it was yes that if
for sure became a relatively lifeless
regurgitation of kind of just compliance
on the models which was too bad because
ideally those models kind of can crack
open places that are stuck in a field or
a discipline and then and it allowed new
shoots to grow the map not meeting the
territory was just one of the grandest
ironies of the integral movement because
it was parotid all the time by the
people who were 100% obsessed with the
map and not getting outside and roaming
around and so that was another things it
felt like there was a a very strong
bifurcation but the people who were
drawn to the integral movement and on
the one hand much smaller number but
essential to the life of the movement
were people who were actually arguably
already awake or realized themselves in
the sense that they were living in the
territory and and then there were all
the sort of late majority of the people
who were drawn by the contact hiya Ken's
writings and the methodology itself and
because of Ken's
broad sweep because of his synthetic
analysis of a lot of disciplines all of
this and because of the sort of
confidence bordering on hubris with
which he held forth and proclaimed the
nature of things if somebody hadn't done
their own primary research and wasn't
deeply versed in the disciplines that he
was presuming to speak of
they took his his synthesis and analysis
as gospel and never went back and did
the hard work of reading the original
sources and drawing their own companions
or triangulating between other experts
and leaders in those given disciplines
but the folks that felt like they were
walking the turret like I don't I'm not
sure integral actually woke anybody up
so point was you know the same way the
critique of Christ as he made Christians
not Christ Buddha made Buddhists not
Buddha's you know that the Bruce Lee
didn't make another Bruce Lee so lineage
of the son of a bitch but the people
that I experienced and valued the most
who were a light with their own lived
experience came from what I could tell
from the Adi Dada lineage there was a
bunch of those including Sophia Diaz
David da data some of some of those
folks Thierry Patton they were they were
folks that had clearly been lit up
by a transmitter in the past chögyam
trungpa was another linear source where
people were drawn to this work but had
been sparked previously potentially some
Osho although I didn't have one-on-one
direct recognition of those folks in the
mix and that was my sense is that the
people who were already awake got there
some by other means and then were drawn
to that work post facto to explain their
own lived experience and the people who
were drawn to it purely from the
intellectual line or domain it simply
entrenched them even further in hyper
cognition and disembodiment then it set
them free yeah because I I feel I mean
when I introduced you in the beginning I
said I thought you were holding a really
important piece and that from reading
stealing fire and spending a little bit
of time with you I think is that
embodied flow state get out of your
minds get into the the liminal
experience which is something I really
identify with with the piece that you're
bringing and that's the piece you say
that was not present with integral yeah
I mean you know we've all got our biases
so we for sure you know we can only
become more of what we are he was a
Eastern non-dual meditator so out of all
traditions he wildly privileged those
and he was a weightlifter body builder
judo so so that became his triangle of
proving it to academia Eastern and
particularly you know some Shen and some
varying other fairly esoteric spaces
saying that those were the pinnacle of
the Eastern contemplative tract and
there is nothing but non dual suchness
and then like I'm yoked you know and
this is this is embodiment and so those
just became you know we all come in
through certain doorways but as he
justified those to the exclusion of
other things I think that's when his his
laser beams became a little tunnel
focused I mean one classic examples I
remember him dismissing the entire
Burning Man culture and movement
as deep red which in the terminology of
spiral dynamics was son a very primitive
and tribal so very very low down the
ladder of what could be cool and you
know six or seven steps below
second-tier or integral the the domain
that he and his community were claiming
and the reality was he hadn't been and
he had done it by reading the ten
principles wrote that time maybe there
were six or seven but what he you know
completely just missed and that
assessment was those were lowest common
denominator rules upon which a full
rainbow of descriptions and expressions
were also taking place so it was that
kind of you know when all you gots a
hammer everything looks like a nail when
all you've gots a hyper cognitive
complex map that dice X things all
you've got our parts and pieces even if
there's something vibrant that's not in
your personal preference but might be an
emerging thing of interest to keep tabs
on do you think that the the
developmental piece and in particular
the the kind of color based value
systems piece is useful to get out of
the culture war dynamic mmm I mean just
like an understanding of those different
mimetic value systems and how they
interact perceive each other that kind
of thing yeah I mean the first thing is
I think that you know spiral dynamics
sort of firmly jump the shark when can
change the colors to align with the
chakras that would be the place I would
back it off run and while you're at it
you might as well leave dawn graves
behind and go all done back and go all
the way back to Clare graves if you want
an understanding of spiral dynamics it
lost all of its nuance and most of its
usefulness by the time that got
simplified into the versions that most
people are conversing with today so that
said you know back to you know hard
lessons learned from the field in the
management consulting space we initially
introduced spiral dynamics levels of
development and of course every hyper
agentic peak orange business achiever
you know type-a personality instantly
looks at any map model or ranking system
and sees themselves at the top and
either insists they already are there or
wants to get there as soon as fuckin
possible and so
several years of spectacular wipeouts
and organizational shit shows as a
result of introducing that we actually
deliberately broke the ladder and then
rearrange the colors and laid them out
horizontally and said these are
different mindsets or worldviews here's
how you message as different mindsets
and do so with basically equal embrace
of all the humans and humanity contained
therein
so the challenge with any of these
vertical models is good old-fashioned
human nature it's dr. Seuss and yertle
the turtle you know I want to be king of
the palm so stack me up as high as I can
go on the backs of all the other turtles
and you know arguably the only people
that can really hold a hierarchic
ranking system and not succumb to egoic
by passing are the people who no longer
need it or you know deeply embodied it
already so as far as Ken's Ken's
discussion of the mean green mean I mean
I think it's I think it's cultural
analysis of pathological baby-boomer
value systems is spot-on and weirdly I
thought there was a bullet in that son
of a bitch in the in the early to mid
90s I thought like post-modernism had
officially crawled up its own asshole
and died and that was the time I was in
graduate school in the social sciences
you know we kind of ran that sucker off
the cliff but what's interesting is that
Millennials are now reviving what Ken
calls Boomer Aegeus or the Mean Green
meme and what is even more problematic
about the Millennials cut out it is they
didn't even build it in the first place
they just inherited it and so they don't
even know what it was built in
opposition to aka 1950s 1960s class
warfare militarization gender emergence
social Awakening etc they just take it
as their birthright of the way things
should be so weirdly I thought that Ken
was fighting the last war on on kind of
on boomer Aegis or the Mean Green meme
it has come back like a zombie and is
now completely infecting social justice
warrior kind of stuff and the far-left
reactionary movements these days that
said from the developmental perspective
I think and and this is not normally
what kin did
but I think his his discussion of green
in all of those caricatured pathological
ways it's not in keeping with the rest
of the academic literature on
individualist the individualist stage
which is what some of the jain Levenger
and suzanne cook writer and others who
were the actual academics in this field
looked at and the individualist stage
AKA green is actually much more
comprehensive and has lots of pro-social
and overall positive capacities and
developments and I feel like in Ken's
labeling it of MGM mean green mean
boomer itis whatever you want to call it
that a lot of that got eclipsed not just
in his own critique and analysis but in
an awful lot of people following him and
so I think that was problematic now that
said ah things like alright and far left
culture wars that are happening today
can you know can we gain some insights
from looking at that lenses or colors of
cultural you know pneumatics yes
does it give us any powerful or profound
insights as to what to do about it
no not as sure and what else did you
learn from trying to I guess enact
integral theory at the hard at the sharp
end well the simplest is just no one
gives a shit right you can be as clever
as you want and business leaders any any
anybody in actual life whether it's
here's the 17 different levels of
parenting and how to bring your little
shot you know people want to know how do
I keep my baby who's colicky crying
tonight how do I get them to sleep and
when you bring it into a business
situation I mean we we brought some of
the most comprehensive fully dimension
aqua kosher approaches into businesses
and quite often even had the you know
fully drank the kool-aid buy-in of the
CEOs / founders so we had cut lunch in a
way that you never do in bigger
companies or coming in through HR to do
a training like we had massive
permission to play and we did everything
from Bobby bodily stuff to communication
practices to maps and models to theories
I mean just did it all and destroyed
shareholder value wasted so much time
ended up you know blowing out the backs
of those engagements a year later 18
months later because we were costing a
ton of money and taking a ton of time
enforcing enforcing that people develop
grow up take on tools and models that
had no clear relevance to their business
their work or their lives and no one
could handle that much change while
still doing their day jobs
so as a result of that like we kept on
pruning and simplifying and pruning and
simplifying till five years later we
didn't even talk about the quadrants the
simplest element of Ken's stuff we just
simply talked about and we didn't then
then we reduced the four to the three we
call it the I that we in the it then
realized that was even too abstract we
called it individuals teams and
organizations so like Dorothy and The
Wizard of Oz you know we had to go all
the way through integral complexity to
come back to using terms that were
pretty self-evident
there's employees there's groups of
employees and there's all of us together
in this company we run and work in and
so by the time you could break it down
to terms that were actionable and useful
in the real world as people actually
lived and worked in the real world
you're back to truisms and and really
kind of self-evident common-sense things
which is fine but there was 10 years
there where and Fred Kaufmann was
another one he founded a company called
excellent none of them worked and and
neither did I integral Institute as a
business and that's not to say that you
know money and profits are the sole
thing but if one of the truth claims is
this model or theory is more
sophisticated complex and inclusive
therefore more effective and
organizations like the UN ought to be
adopting it to solve the problems of the
world and you can't even create a cash
flow positive business out of it that
should be a signal that something's not
quite right in what's going on and how
would you summarize that not quite right
well I mean again I think you know that
notion of like crack fries burgers kids
it's just too clever for its own fucking
good and that's not to say that certain
clever people want to think in that way
or right in that way
or even read read things written in that
way but it is to have some humility of
the sort of everybody's got a plan until
they get hit you know Mike Tyson 101 and
it was it was almost the equivalent of
you know like in Raiders of the Lost Ark
you know Indiana Jones goes out into
that Moroccan square and there's that
black Saracen and he's whips out his
scimitar and does all this fancy ass
stuff and then that you know Indy just
picks out his gun and shoots him right
and and that's kind of life and you know
aqwal theory was a little bit like the
dude with the scimitar which is an awful
lot of arm waving without nearly enough
practical grounded connection to the
task at hand
and do you have any other criticisms or
thoughts about it yeah I mean you know
there's been lots of solid and
methodical breakdowns of you know where
integral Theory got out over its key
specifically its orienting
generalizations and you know presuming
to define entire academic disciplines
with a certain straw man that then would
get knocked down I think ken was clearly
strongest in the realm of developmental
psychology and Eastern Kentucky of
traditions and that and that's and
that's his earlier work for the most
part and it's you know that's where I
think he was really drawing from his
wheelhouse the so there's critiques
there kind of within the ad within the
frameworks and that's been done but the
biggest one the biggest - for me we're
simply the notion of it didn't work as a
business nor did any other businesses
find ways to make it work so just pure
proof of concept product market fit and
the other one which i think is as big is
one of integrals biggest you know true
claims to fame was that Eastern
contemplative traditions are partial
because they don't address psychological
shadow Western psychological traditions
don't address non-dual ness
or or sort of attainment and integral is
the best of both worlds because we have
non giannis with awareness of shadow and
then ken promptly went on to endorse
every fucked up dysfunctional guru on
the planet pretty much I mean I mean
maybe this was our field so we certainly
knew these ones but everyone from not
backing away from Adi da to
King and co-leading everything under the
Sun with Andrew Cohen to mock Gaffney to
gampa Roshi to robert augustus market
masters i mean the list was pretty much
endless as to the the gurus with feats
of clay and and that's problematic
because if the very thing we said we
could do we consistently spectacularly
fail at ourselves to say nothing of ken
himself and the blind spots of the
single you know the hero with a thousand
helpers business model if it's not
helping us do the very thing we claim it
does better than anything else that's a
problem why do you think that happened
that specifically I mean obviously it's
the humans involved and and on some
level is there some mutual back
scratching as peers and colleagues agree
to come to be complicit together on each
other's platforms to further increase
their reach and scope and you know
business and incomes for sure and that
happens even more these days with
Instagram likes and podcasts reach and
all that kind of stuff so I think
there's many times that people will look
the other way over small things and
large because of reach and scope and
mutual benefit but I think fundamentally
it's it's it was hubris and and anybody
that proclaims a model of everything is
gonna miss something that something
doesn't show up on that map and it's
fundamentally
I mean for me my sensory is anything
that presumes a pinnacle attainment the
moment said you know the moment a
teacher hints implies or outright states
but they have achieved a zone of
realization that is extraordinary first
you know I think that you set yourself
up for the bifurcation the accumulation
of shadow it seems I mean you basically
just hinted at that there like this this
Eastern model of enlightenment as a kind
of final destination just seems to be is
that the problem because it seems that
as soon as any personal organization is
built around that model it just almost
invariably seems to end up in shadow
yeah I mean I think that's one of the
biggest problems in the sort of
spiritual marketplace in general and
whether it's Byron Katie Eckhart Tolle
Jed McKenna any of the kind of like
crypto neo Vedanta you know the idea
that kind of like the world is illusory
it's all in your mind
and just changing your mind is gonna
change everything and often smuggle in
together with that is something along
the lines of there is such a thing as
instantaneous irreversible enlightenment
and I think whether or not there are
humans on the planet at any point in
time that have achieved something like
that is a whole other question but I
think it's a shitty teaching technique
regardless and so because what happens
is the moment a person in the position
of authority has claimed irreversible
state of perfectibility
then all shadow that arises in the
intersubjective the conversations and
the living between you and me is now no
longer me and it has to all be you and
then even when there's clearly some
stuff I'm doing this batshit crazy out
of line I can't go hey you're right I
had a bad
I have to hold behind that Plexiglas
wall and say I must I'm still perfect
therefore I did that on purpose
therefore even though it seemed like a
shitty thing it's actually crazy wisdom
in service of your awakening and therein
that's the beginning of the end and so
every time I come across any teacher or
teaching that is making any claims along
those lines you like don't go near it no
matter how alive a light shining no
matter how much they're waking people up
with charismatic transmission
it just feels problematic and so that's
why teachers like Pema Chodron you know
who emphasize our humanity you know I
mean I think in a nutshell I think
spirituality is wildly overrated and I
think our core humanity is wildly
underrated and so the teachers that I
can get behind other ones Pema Chodron
Alice Walker as you know it's just a
wisdom holder adyashanti like folks who
are like yeah this is it this is us and
and get used to it and the way out is
through the way out is down and in up
and away those those experiences just
feel more honest to me and we don't end
up in the schizoid effort to reconcile
than that the utter tragedy that is the
human experience with all of these
ascendant so-called spiritual states or
experiences do you think I'm guessing
the answer might well be no but do you
think that integral has some relevance
or could could still be relevant to the
conversation today yeah I mean it's a
great question in some respects the
advice I always give folks is I think
that integral theory should be deeply
studied and then promptly forgotten you
know like keep it as kind of operating
system virusscan keep it as kind of pegs
to hang things on keep it in or use it
as a sort of rubric
against which you check to make sure
you're not missing something obvious but
in general the I just don't think that
life submits
to that form of false precision very
well or helpfully it does feel like in
fact a buddy of ours a co-author with
Ken on his integral life practice book
Adam Leonard is one of the lead
executive development folks at Google
now and we were just having a
conversation a couple of weeks ago and
he and he's been having great traction
lately bringing in integrally informed
concepts into the executive leadership
at Google framed around VUCA conditions
volatile uncertain complex ambiguous and
the idea that we need to increase our
complexity of sense-making
in order to handle the challenges ahead
and frame that way and filtered that way
I think that integral insights and
perspectives are invaluable but simply
dumped wholesale on the table and said
build with this because it's better
hasn't worked out as well as it might
and and the final piece is you know
implicit really one of the sent the long
tentpoles of the integral argument is
the growth to goodness idea the idea
that in vertical development we end up
moving up the spiral or moving up the
ladder whatever the metaphor is going to
be and that going from first tier to
second tier second tier is better going
from you know the green mean to teal or
purple or you know aqua or whatever he
was calling it at the lost last count is
better and there was an implicit idea
that we become more sage like more
enlightened more compassionate more of
all the good pro-social things that we
value as humanity and the jury is very
much out on that the jury's a very much
out on developmental theory as a true
model Zack Stein has been talking about
interestingly kind of the acquisition of
skills an ecosystem of self that the
higher reached its states of awareness
being meaning-making etcetera are
temporary vulnerable dependent on
environment depending on scaffolding
that we can be up in these places at
different times
in different aspects of ourselves and
you can have high-functioning sociopath
you can have you know Nazis were
infinitely more complex than Yanomami
tribesmen in the Amazon and they didn't
just make trains run on time right and
so then there's been research on the
spread of EQ or emotional intelligence
training and findings that the worst
thing you can possibly do is teach EQ
skills to sociopaths and Psychopaths and
pick up culture was a you know hat which
has weird overlaps with the integral
community via some of the communication
dialogue processes started out as pickup
artistry and so you realize that you
know a hundred percent use of the force
gives you Yoda and ninety-nine percent
use of the force gives you death they do
and so I think it's really critical back
to like our humanity is that I would
take an old grandma in her rocking chair
on the front porch sharing rootsy
down-home wisdom it's not complex at all
you know over sum over cognitive asshat
you know trying to map things in Tetra
arising dimensions and and the same
thing with you know second tier men in
particular who so imbalanced in their
embodiment and even their you know
absolutely lack of backbone and
conviction I'd rather deal with you know
blue like honor Duty courage sacrifice
men who recognize that there is in fact
something bigger than their own
experience or process to live and die
for and then you're just like hey gotcha
that's all so now can we expand what it
is you bow down to all right can we just
add the computer some possibility to the
thing you serve verse is trying to find
men in you know men the men from Marin
right who are so about counting the
angels on the head of a pin that their
balls in their backbone are nowhere to
be found and I'm going to take longer
than we've got to grow anew do you have
anything that you would say to Ken
himself hmm well bottom line thank you
thank you for living your life
expressing your Dhamma taking that bad
ass mind of yours and using it to split
atoms and map reality you know I think
you you've informed a generation of
thinkers beers and doers and I think the
world is absolutely a better place for
you having walked your walk and thought
your thoughts because of it as I said at
the beginning the the nature of the the
internet and the the kind of emergent
conversation is that it has to be
two-way and there is a sense with I know
that there's a sense within a lot of
people who are following integral that
integral needs to be part of this
conversation it needs to be part of the
developmental framework for example
would really help inform the
intellectual darkweb argument but I
think for that to happen it would also
need for integral and Ken to be open to
to feedback into dialogue in a way that
perhaps we haven't seen so far do you
think that they are open to that yeah I
mean I haven't touched base in that
world and honestly I mean my sense where
where it can
lost the most relevance other than the
kind of collapse of integral Institute
was in the no longer going ban I get it
like when you've got a complex thought
structure and you're interested on the
leading edge of your newest ideas having
to go back and re-establish all this all
the stepping stones it's just a ball
lake and for him to be discussing you
know almost glibly
chakra systems or subtle energy or
things that are very far off the
reservation even skeptical enthusiasts
and discussing them as if they are
established facts that to me is
problematic you're like okay you've
broken with any efforts to maintain
relevance to the middle of the bell
curve including including someone like
me who just prefer
a sort of agnostic Gnosticism he prefers
a kind of rational mysticism versus
taking other things on lock stock and
barrel the the feedback loops I haven't
seen can being open to it and I think
there's legitimate peevishness on his
part in the same way that Jordan
Peterson clearly got increasingly kind
of hijacked and reactive you know before
and immediately after the launch of his
book as he was a taking and Sam Harris
for that matter right just potshots and
slings and arrows and at some point you
take a swipe at the ankle-biters and so
you know critiques it can you know that
it's the wheat from the chaff really
like the critiques of Ken that are just
inflammatory reactionary don't get it
caricature typecast yeah you know what
yeah that's a waste of time to have to
sift through those if you've got actual
Dhamma real work to go and do but the
considered open-hearted critiques have
to be met with something more than you
just don't understand the model or
you're misinterpreting it has to be like
okay I've got my boat the ship I'm
steering through the water and I've got
my wake and I don't always notice my
wake but if it's upsetting other
people's boats if it's slamming up
against dachshunds whomping picnics I
need to take responsibility for that and
I think that that piece somewhere
between the non-dual and the and the
psychological is that is the span where
ken was actually had the least vision
and that was the messy human parts of
how we get this done together and there
and the way we inform and are informed
by each other and where is the cutting
edge of the conversation now where where
should people go to if integral felt
like the cutting edge of the
conversation in sort of 90s 2000s where
is that cutting edge right now do you
think well I mean I think topically that
thing that I'm trying to track them most
right now and I think it's essential for
our collective future and one and the
least developed is
the culture that we began mapping and
stealing fire but is clearly showing up
in a lot of different ways around the
world and in the intellectual dark web
is a part of it yeah which is what is
the emergence of transpersonal
collective emergent culture so
specifically what happens when we get
together and basically connect in serial
almost like a bunch of computers to
create a collective supercomputer that
is non hierarchical there's not one
person at the top of that pyramid and
that's not flattening that's not to say
we're all gonna get an endless process
and share our feelings this dynamic
subordination it is a high-functioning
collaborative process so what does
basically what do basically ethical
cults look like you know if you had
traditional cults were you know like the
loose Tinian mysteries of the Dionysian
cult or anything like that through
history just from an anthropological
perspective that was subjugation of self
to the lineage which of the tradition
and then we ended up with culty cults
you know which was Charles Manson and
Jim Jones and potentially Andrew Cohen
and some and audio and some of these
others and that was subjugation of the
self to the Guru who was a ronin they
were they were not they were not a
samurai with the dojo they just taken
their own claim and said I am God
realized and that was obviously wildly
problematic but we sort of Rini to
reclaim the original intentions cultist
from latin just means to worship and
what happens when we get together and
worship or experience ecstasy speak
experiences together how do we make
ethical cults where the individual is
not subsumed but actually the serenity
of every individual is paramount and
then we collect in we connect in
co-creative emergence that is a son of a
bitch and I haven't seen anybody outside
of you know a week or two building a
camp at Burning Man or you know
high-performing sports teams or special
operations I mean they think the only
places I've seen it have been in
temporary or explicitly
performance-driven meaning they're
high-performing teams professional
basketball or hockey or suddenly that or
special operations and if you can
cut it in that game of dynamic
subordination you're out and the next
person who can has put in place and so
to do this in egalitarian non
hierarchical community we live in an
urban area together we're trying to make
sense of that we are building an
intentional community together and we're
all in this together
anything that doesn't mean I can just
can you when you underperform I haven't
yet seen us figure that out so for me
that's the cutting edge of this
conversation is we all know enough to be
dangerous how do we get together and and
make newer and more complicated mistakes
together not repeat the old ones that
really tracks with I guess we're where
we're at as well on the channel people
like Jordan green halt yourself Daniel
shmatte Tim burger the question is how
do we create into subject genuine into
subjective sense making
yeah and it's a son of a bitch and what
you said earlier about like how quickly
would the aqwal seemed of devoted to
who's more integral than thou who has
privileged claims truth claims to source
whatever the source this subscribes
source can be and it can be aqwal theory
it could be five Meo DMT and the fine
and the hyperspace gods it could be it
doesn't really matter what gets posited
up there but the moment that becomes the
vehicle by which we're all supposed to
gather together we still have
discernment judgment trade offs
allocation of power money resources
sexuality you name it all the tribal
monkey stuff and as soon as it devolves
in any way shape or form to a either
exclusive claims of weapon Asst right I
mean and I I have abiding and
unchallengeable access to source or is
just a shit show dogfight every time
that's when any emergence collapses and
we're back to game theory 101 and and I
have not seen any way around that other
than potentially couples and I'd like
this is super provisional but
potentially like couples then connecting
to each other and attempting to maybe do
this in groups of say 12 you know like
12 humans 12 couples not sure but the
ante as Daniel would say the
Antti decoherence the attendance II of
us to actually stay in it together when
everything wants to fling us or drive us
apart I don't think that Burning Man
culture is adequate for it I don't think
that nonviolent communication is
adequate for it I mean in my own
experience everything I've got with my
partner including decades under the
bridge growing up together two children
that we know and love and know that we
would harm if we ever broke apart right
vibrant personal intimate practice
together reassert like literally making
love all the time and adding that to the
tank like we have every reason in the
world to stay in this through the
hardest stuff and it still gets down to
metal on metal and there's times where
it's like fuck you fuck this I'm out
so knowing my own experience where like
it's like holy shit we have everything
on our side everything possible you know
to help us stay together and it's still
the liveliest ride of our lives how how
on earth are we gonna do this at scale
is a question I think about every day
[Music]
you